Guide to the Harold Cruse Papers TAM.187
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
- Series III: Writings, 1940-2005; 8.02 Linear Feet in 2 record cartons, 2 half manuscript boxes, 7 manuscript boxes, 1 flat box, and 1 oversized flat box
  - "Interludes with Duke Ellington", ca.1982-1985 (Box 4, Folder 18, Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Interview with Harold Cruse (Transcript), 2000 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - A Lady of Consequence, 1962 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - London Diary, 1969-1970 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - "Marxism and Negritude", undated (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - "Marxism and Negritude Part Three", undated (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - "Marxism and the Negro", undated (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - "Marxism and Negro Literature", undated (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - "Marxism and the Negro Question", undated (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - "Memoirs of a Self-Taught Journalist", undated (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - More Than Just a Politicians: Notes on the Life and Times of Harold Cruse (Van Gosse), 2000, 2004 (Box 14, Folder 8-9)
  - "My Jewish Problem and Theirs", 1969 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Negro Culture: Heritage and Weapon (Review by Cruse), undated (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - "A Negro Looks at Cuba", undated (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - "Negro Nationalism's New Wave", undated (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - "The Negro Playwright", undated (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - "Negro Soldier Sequences Censored in 'Call Me Mister'", 1951 (Box 14, Folder 11)
  - "The Negro Writer - Disarmed, Dis[en]franchised, Disoriented", 1967 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - "The New Afro Americanism", undated (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - "The New Negro History of John Hope Franklin", 1980, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - "The New Negro History of John Hope Franklin - Promise and Progress", undated (Box 14, Folder 12)
  - Notebooks / Journals (2), undated (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Notes: Robeson book, undated (Box 4, Folder 32a)
  - Of Marms and Maids, 1963 (Box 14, Folder 13)
  - "On Explaining Twentieth Century Negro History", undated (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - "On Robert Brustein's Theater Visions", 1979 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Plural But Equal - Review of, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Plural but Equal, 1990, 1995 (Box 14, Folder 14)
  - "The Politics of Negro Business", undated (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - "A Preface to Leadership", undated (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - "Problems in Black Political Philosophy - Exploratory Paper" (Delivered at Morgan State University), 1978 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - "Proposal for a Collected Edition of the Essays", undated (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - "Purblind Slant of Africa", 1951 (Box 14, Folder 15)
  - "Race and Bohemians in Greenwich Village", 1960 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - "Race Riots and Remedies", 1964 (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Rebellion or Revolution - Review of, undated (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - "Revolutionary Nationalism and the Afro-American", undated (Box 14, Folder 16)
  - "The Roots of Black Nationalism", undated (Box 14, Folder 17)
  - "Salute to Josephine Baker, Magnificent Negro Artist", 1951 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Simply Heavenly and Stella Holt - A Viewpoint, undated (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - "The Sociology of Afro Americanism", undated (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - Teaching and Sharing the Humanities: A College for Human Services Value Conference, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - "Three Faces West" - A Western Film Scenario (by Cruse), undated (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - "Towards the Americal Social Theory: The Dialectics of Racial Integration", undated (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Untitled Essays, Poems, and Plays, undated (Box 15, Folder 3-5, Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Untitled Typescript - "Despite many new features of the present day Negro rebellion, this rebellion has its roots in the accumulated experiences of the past fifty years...", undated (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - Untitled Typescript - re: CAUSA and Negroes (pp 173-240), undated (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - Untitled Typescript - "'The Crisis of the Negro Intellectual' was first published...", undated (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - Untitled Typescript - re: Freedom Now Party, William Worthy, etc., undated (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - Untitled Typescript - "In addition, we are being told by the white left...", undated (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - Untitled Typescript - "In 1940, in one of my first acts in the pursuit of becoming a more 'social' being...", undated (Box 4, Folder 52)
  - Untitled Typescript - "In 1964, the special Freedom ways Harlem issue was enlarged...", undated (Box 4, Folder 53)
  - Untitled Typescript - "It was June in Italy, 1944, a languorous summer's day, when Juddie Jones, Negro truck driver, US Army, returned...", undated (Box 4, Folder 54)
  - Untitled Typescripts - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Untitled Typescript - re: "Marxism and the Negro", undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Untitled Typescript - "The nearest living contact I have ever had with French culture was in North Africa during World War Two...", undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Untitled Typescript - "When the Socialist Workers Party (Trotskyist) announced in New York on January 14 that it had nominated a Negro...", undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Village Voice Editorial - "Reading Michael Harrington's report on the Vancouver meeting...", undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - "W.E.B. DuBois and Black History", 2003 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - "What is a Program", undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - "What is Nationalism", undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - "Why an Afro American Cultural Philosophy is Necessary Today", undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - "Where the Hummingbird Flies" - A Critique, undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Series IV: Personal Materials, 1940-2003; 2.44 Linear Feet in 2 manuscript boxes, 1 half manuscript box, and 1 oversized flat box
  This series contains photographs of Harold Cruse, his family, and his travels. It also includes a scrapbook and documents relating to Cruse's military service during World War II; curricula and classwork related to Cruse's undergraduate film studies program; copies of his curriculum vitae and address books; and a resolution honoring Harold Cruse issued by the city of Los Angeles. Together, these materials reflect Cruse's life outside his career in academia.
  - Address Book & Contact Lists, undated (Box 15, Folder 7, Box 16, Folder 1-3)
  - Binder with Undergraduate Coursework, circa 1950s (Box 20, Folder 1-9)
  - Harold Cruse Caricature, 1993 (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Harold Cruse Curriculum Vitae, 1982, 1987 (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Harold Cruse Resolution - City of Los Angeles, 1983 (Box Shared Tamiment 174, Folder 13)
  - Information about Film Schools and Programs, 1947-1952 (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Photographs -- Brown University, 2000 (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - Photographs -- Cleveland University, circa 1970s? (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - Photographs -- England, Wales, and Ireland, 1972 (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - Photographs -- General, undated (Box 16, Folder 10)
  - Photographs -- Harold Cruse, circa 1940s-2000s (Box 16, Folder 11-12)
  - Photographs -- Harold Cruse and Family, circa 1970s, 1981, 2003 (Box 16, Folder 13)
  - Photographs -- Harold Cruse's House on Anderson St., 1972 (Box 16, Folder 14)
  - Photographs -- Harold Cruse and Unidentified People, undated (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Photographs -- Michigan, 1968 (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Photographs -- Switzerland, undated (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Photographs -- U.S. Virgin Islands, circa 2000 (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Photographs -- Yugoslavia, France, Croatia, and Monaco, 1971 (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - Photographs -- Zagreb, Croatia, undated (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - Scrapbook, undated (Box 20, Folder 10-13)
  - World War II Service -- Log of Medical Detachment for 28th Quartermaster Regiment (Xerox Copy), 2003 (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - World War II Service -- Memorabilia, 1941-1947 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - World War II Service -- North Africa Pamphlet (Copy), 1994 (Box 17, Folder 8)